We got some pretty major news out of
OpenAI today. They just released their
openweight model that they've been
promising for a few months now and I
think it's a lot better than most people
were expecting, especially for an
openweight model. So, this brand new
model is called GPTOSS
and it comes in two flavors, two sizes,
right? You've got GPTOSS 120 billion
parameter and GPTOSS 20B which is a lot
less parameters but should be a lot
faster and be able to run on more
machines. They also released them under
the Apache 2.0 license, meaning that
people can download these models,
fine-tune them how they want, and pretty
much iterate off of this model. And I do
believe this is going to be the new
openw weight king. I don't believe that
any of the llama models or mist models
or any of the other open models are
nearly as powerful as this one that just
came out. Now, if you're wondering why
would you care about one of these openw
weight models, openweight models can be
downloaded to your computer and run
completely offline. You don't need
internet access to run these. You do
need a pretty decent GPU to run them,
but you don't need internet access. So,
you can be having chats with your AI of
choice while 30,000 ft in the air on a
plane or if the internet goes out at
your house, but you still need to have
conversations with a chat GPT like bot.
You can do that with these openw weight
models. Also, none of the data gets sent
to the cloud. So, whatever conversations
you have with one of these models, it's
not getting sent to Google or OpenAI or
Microsoft or whoever. It all stays
locally on your computer. Nobody can see
any of the conversations you have with
these models. It's also completely free
to use. Once you have it downloaded on
your computer, it's yours to use. So,
you don't have to pay a ChatGpt or a
Claude or a Google fee to use these
models at all. They're yours. They're on
your computer running locally now. So
let's take a peek at some of the details
around this model and then we'll
actually try to run it and see what it
can do. So again, two models, 120
billion parameter, 20 billion parameter.
It's using a mixture of experts model,
meaning that it's kind of not pinging
all of the parameters at once. It's just
pinging a segment of 5.1 billion
parameters or 3.6 billion parameters,
which theoretically, you know, speeds up
the inference when using these models.
It's also got a context length of
128,000 tokens, meaning between combined
input and output, you're going to be
able to use about 96,000
words. If we take a peek at the
benchmarks here in the code force
competition code benchmark, we can see
that the 120 billion parameter model got
a 2,622 score. If we look at 03 and 04
Mini, the current state-of-the-art
pretty much best models Chat GPT has
right now, it's pretty on par. It just
performed slightly worse than those, but
I mean very slightly. And it actually
outperforms 03 Mini by quite a bit. In
this humanity's last exam, these
openweight models perform about on par
as 04 Mini. On Healthbench, it actually
performs close to 03 and better than 04
and 03 mini. In competition math, it
actually outscores 03 and 03 mini and
just barely gets beat out by 04 mini.
So, these models are really good at math
and code. In the GPQA, which is Google
proof, meaning stuff that you can't
really just find the answer on Google.
The 120 billion parameter model
outperformed 03 and performs pretty on
par with 03 and 04 Mini. And again,
openweight model, free to use, can
download on your computer, and it is
pretty close to matching the current
state-of-the-art closed models from
OpenAI. It's pretty mind-blowing,
honestly. These are also chain of
thought models. So when you give it your
prompt, you can actually see it think
through the prompt and then you can sort
of give it the amount of thinking you
want it to do. So you can have it think
for short, medium, or longer term so
that it better sort of logics through
the response. And they're available
right now. You can download them on
hugging face and you can run them in
tools like Olama and LM Studio and
Together AI and all of these various
services here. I tend to use LM Studio
and that's what we'll use in a minute
when we test this out. But just a few
other things I want to show you. Sam
Alman tweeted as soon as this went live,
GPT OSS is out. We made an open model
that performs at the level of 04 mini
and runs on a high-end laptop. That's
stretching. I mean, like if you're using
the 120 billion parameter model here, it
does say it requires an 80 GB GPU, which
there aren't many consumer GPUs that
will do that. If you have a high-end Mac
Studio, you can run it on a high-end Mac
Studio. I actually have a Mac Studio
with 256
GB of RAM. So, I should be able to run
this model. We'll find out in a minute.
But the smaller 20 billion parameter
model can run with just 16 GB of memory,
which you can get on most modern
consumer GPUs. Now, I went to Perplexity
real quick and said, which GPUs have 16
GB of VRAM or more? And we can see
there's a few AMD Radeon models, RTX
5060, 5070, 5080, of course the 5090,
the 4080s, 4090s, 3090s, 3090 Ti. Quite
a bit of GPUs that can run the model
that requires 16 GB. And here's some
more detailed thoughts from Sam on this
new model. GPT OSS is a big deal. It's a
state-of-the-art openweight reasoning
model with strong real world performance
comparable to 04 Mini that you can run
locally on your own computer or phone
with the smaller size. We believe this
is the best and most usable open model
in the world. He says he wants to get it
in the hands of as many people as
possible and that we believe far more
good than bad will come from it. The 120
billion parameter model performs about
as well as 03 on challenging health
issues and they've worked to mitigate
the most serious safety issues
especially around biocurity. Although we
believe most people will want to use a
convenient service like chat GPT people
should be able to directly control and
modify their own AI when they need to
and the privacy benefits are obvious cuz
you can do it completely offline. We
expect a meaningful uptick in the rate
of innovation in our field and for many
more people to do important work than
were able to do before. It also looks
like this is going to be the model
that's going to be used in the future on
Windows PCs. As part of today's release,
Microsoft is also bringing GPU optimized
versions of the GPTO OSS 20B model to
Windows devices. If this is good at
code, this could honestly replace Claude
for a lot of people because it's an open
model, meaning you're not paying API
fees every time you need to use code.
And well, Claude code keeps on bumping
up their prices. If you could do this
all locally on your own computer, you're
not worried about API cost. You're just
worried about your own power usage of
your own computer. So, let's go ahead
and actually install this on our
computer. If you're into branding of any
kind, this will change your workflow.
Recraft is an AI image generation tool
built for designers. You can create
consistent, highquality illustrations,
logos, mockups, and icons without giving
up creative control. Say you need vector
art. Recraft is the only AI that
generates real SVGs. I picked a style,
typed my prompt, create a banner for my
Mattwolf YouTube channel main page about
AI and tech, and got a scalable design
instantly. Some of you may know I have a
website called futuretools.io io where I
review and rate AI tools. It's run by a
pretty scrappy team, so we don't have a
ton of branding besides this logo. Let's
see if Recraft can help. I'm going to
upload the logo as a reference image,
and Recraft instantly generates
consistent onbrand assets I can use
across the website and anywhere else I
need branding like slide decks or on
YouTube. This feature alone just saved
me hours of work. Recraft is already
used by teams at Netflix, Oglev,
HubSpot, so you know you can trust the
output. Check out the link in the
description where you can start creating
with ReCraft for free today. Thank you
so much to Recraft for sponsoring this
one. Now, let's get back to the video.
So, let's go ahead and actually install
this on our computer. To do that, I'm
going to use LM Studio. I'm going to
head on over to lmstudio.ai.
Download it for Mac. Obviously, download
it for whatever operating system you're
using. and we'll go ahead and run the
installer. Drop that here and we'll open
LM Studio local AI on your computer.
Let's get started. I want to be shown
everything, so I'm going to select a
developer, but you choose whatever you
want. And we can see that as soon as we
open LM Studio, it suggests GPTO OSS
20B. And this is the model that most
people are going to want to download and
use, the 120 billion parameter model.
Again, you need a pretty hefty computer
to use. So, let's go ahead and download
GPT OSS20B. Keep in mind it is over 12
GB. So, make sure you have the space for
it. While that's downloading, I'm going
to actually continue into LM Studio
here. And then down in the bottom right
corner, I'm going to click on my
settings. And then I'm going to click on
model search cuz I want to test 120B on
my computer as well. I have a really
high-end Mac Studio that I've never
really pushed it to its limits. So, I'm
going to grab this model here as well.
It is 64 GB, so it's going to take a
while, but uh might as well get that
download going as well. All right, so
our 20 billion parameter model is
downloaded, so we can go ahead and use
that now. And then up at the top, we
have select model to load. We'll go
ahead and select the GPT OSS 20B. And
now we essentially have a model that's
as good as chat GPT offline. Just for
good measure, let's ask how many Rs are
in the word strawberry. It thought for
less than 1 second. The word strawberry
contains three occurrences of the letter
R. Good job. And we can actually see the
thought process as well. Count R letters
in strawberry. And then R appears three
times. Pretty fast, too. 74 tokens per
second. We can also see down at the
bottom here, we can attach images or
PDFs or things like that. We can turn on
additional integrations like the JS code
sandbox and rag v1. We can also install
more integrations straight through MCP
servers. And we can change the reasoning
effort between low, medium, and high.
Here up in the top right, we've got our
little wrench icon. If I click on this,
we have more settings. I could give it a
system prompt, mess with the reasoning
effort over here, change the model
temperature, change the sampling
settings, give information about
structured output, and speculative
decoding over my I can click on program
here and turn on additional
integrations. Let's test a coding
prompt. I'm going to go ahead and click
on new chat and let's have it create a
vampire survivors style game in
JavaScript. I'll say create a vampire
survivors clone using JavaScript so I
can test it in the browser. Under
reasoning effort, I'm going to turn it
on high. And since it is JavaScript,
let's turn on the JS code sandbox. I'm
assuming that will help with JavaScript.
And one last step before I submit this.
I need to click on the settings up next
to the model here and make sure that we
set our context length to the higher
end. It shouldn't need to use this many
tokens cuz it's writing code. But we do
want to crank it up to make sure that it
can actually continue to write the code.
I probably don't need to set it all the
way to the 131,000 tokens. I'm probably
good setting it at like let's go 20,000
tokens. And then I'll reload to apply
changes. And now I'll submit my prompt
and it starts thinking. And this was
really quick. It took maybe I don't know
45 seconds or so to generate all of
this. But it generated a ton of code. We
have two files we can play with an
index.html and the main.js. So just for
the sake of this demo, let's just create
a new folder here. I'm just going to
call it temp for now. Inside our temp
folder, I'll create our index.html file.
So we'll go ahead and copy the text here
for our index.html. create a new
document inside of our temp folder here.
Paste our text in and we'll save this as
our index.html.
We'll create a new document here. Copy
our main.js.
Paste this in here. And we'll save this
as main.js.
Now, theoretically, we should be able to
open our index.html file here and have
our Vampire Survivors game. Now, it's
not doing any shooting, but there are
enemies coming at me, and I'm running
away, and more enemies are coming at the
screen. And you can see I've survived
for, you know, 45 seconds. This
basically just created a simple game
where I'm dodging the characters. So,
yeah, it didn't really make a vampire
survivors game, but hey, it did it
really fast. It did it with an
open-source offline model, and I'm
excited to see what the bigger model
does once that's finally done
downloading. All right, it finally
finished downloading the 120 billion
parameter model. took quite a while.
Again, this is the model that requires
about 80 GB of RAM. As you can see, I've
got 256 GB of RAM and 208 GB of
potential VRAM. So, theoretically, I
should be able to run it. I don't know
how fast it's going to be, but let's
give it a shot. Up at the top, I'm going
to switch this model to our 120B model.
I'll create a new chat here. Let's click
on our settings. Make sure that we crank
up our context length again, just so it
doesn't run out. For our prompt, once
again, I'm going to do create a vampire
survivors clone using JavaScript so I
can test it in the browser. Reasoning
effort, I'm going to switch it to high.
We'll leave the JS code sandbox on. And
it actually ran pretty well. It
generated about 35 tokens per second.
And it generated this code here for me.
And it actually made my life easy. It
put it all in one file. So, I don't have
a separate HTML and JavaScript file. So,
I'll go ahead and copy all of this text
here. Create a new text file. Paste the
whole thing in. We'll save this one as
vampire.html.
And when I open it, I get this. I mean,
he's shooting very, very rapidly, but
it's a much closer clone to vampire
survivors than the 20B model managed to
make, right? I've got the bad guys
coming at me, and it's just
automatically shooting weapons. I mean,
the weapons are a little too aggressive.
It makes it a little too easy. Nobody
can even make it close to me. But, I
mean, one shot from an open-source
model, you know, a couple more prompts
and we've got a solid vampire survivor
code. Honestly, I still can't believe
that this is capable of doing this with
just one prompt. Open source, completely
offline. It's pretty much as good as the
best state-of-the-art models out there
right now, except it's open- source, can
be run completely offline. You're not
sending any data to anybody else's
servers, and it's really, really good.
Like I'm really impressed with what we
can do with this open- source model and
I'm even more excited to see what
happens as people get their hands on it
and they iterate off of it and they
fine-tune it. It's only going to get
better and more uncensored and have more
and more capabilities as people start
playing around with it. So super
exciting to see that we can get the
equivalent of some of the best chat GPT
models for free and offline right now.
And if this wasn't enough news for you,
well, it looks like we might be getting
more this week. Sam Alman went to X
today and said, "We have a lot of new
stuff for you over the next few days.
Something big but small today."
Referring to the GPT OSS we just talked
about and then a big upgrade later this
week. Is that GPT5? I don't know. Could
turn into a really, really exciting
week. This is already pretty dang cool.
I'm here for it. And whatever happens
this week, I will be covering it all in
Saturday's AI news breakdown. Every
Saturday I make a full video where I
demo all of the newest AI capabilities
that we have for the week and talk about
all the latest AI news. So, if you want
more videos like this where I show you
how to use the tools, but also keep you
looped in on all the latest AI news,
make sure you like this video, subscribe
to this channel, and I will make sure
more stuff like this shows up in your
YouTube feed. Thank you so much for
hanging out with me and nerding out with
me today. Thank you to Recraft for
sponsoring this video. Yeah, go play
with this new OSS model. It's totally
free to use. All right, that's all I got
for you. Hopefully I'll see you in the
next one.